Okay, next section is the stomach.
The first disorder is called gastroschisis.
Gastro means, refers to the stomach, and schisis means to split,
so it's as if there's splitting of the stomach.
Now, we don't literally get splitting of the stomach in this disorder.
Instead, we get a congenital malformation of the abdominal wall,
so that it is the abdominal wall that is actually kind of split,
which then leads to exposure of the abdominal contents.
Let me remind you that when we form the abdominal wall,
we actually have a bunch of folds that come together.
So there's an anterior fold, there's a posterior fold,
and then there's a couple lateral folds,
and all of these have to come together to form that anterior abdominal wall.
Now, in this particular case, there is a congenital malformation,
so you don't form the wall.
When you don't form the wall, of course,
there's going to be exposure of the abdominal contents.
And this is what gastroschisis looks like.
You've got a hole in the abdominal wall,
which, again, exposes the gastric contents
so that you can clearly see the intestine.
You're basically directly looking at the intestines.
The next disorder is called omphalocele.
And in this particular case, what happens is you get persistent herniation of the bowel
into the umbilical cord.
Let's go back to development to remind ourselves that
because there was very little space in the abdomen
during the early development of the bowel,
you actually get some herniation of the bowel into the umbilical cord.
And then remember that the bowel undergoes a 90-degree counterclockwise rotation.
And when that rotation occurs, it pulls the bowel back out of the umbilical cord
into the body cavity.
So in this particular case, in an omphalocele, you have persistent herniation.
Now, remember, the herniation was part of development, but it persists.
So you get persistent herniation of the bowel into the umbilical cord.
Again, this is due to a failure of the herniated intestines
to return to the body cavity during development.
Now, interestingly, because you've got this herniation into the umbilical cord,
you're going to see the contents of the abdomen.
However, it's going to be covered by peritoneum and the amnion of the umbilical cord.
So it looks like this.
You see the abdominal contents, but they're present in a bubble.
And, of course, that bubble is the peritoneum and the amnion of the umbilical cord.
So this is very important because it makes for a very clear distinction between gastroschesis.
So in gastroschesis, you have a hole in the anterior abdominal cavity,
or in the, sorry, you have a hole in the abdominal wall
that then reveals the abdominal contents,
whereas in an omphalocele, you have herniation of the bowel,
which also can reveal the abdominal contents.
However, you wouldn't directly see the contents.
It would be covered by this bubble-like surface,
which, again, represents the peritoneum and the amnion of the umbilical cord.
So this is a very important distinction to make here.
Pyloric stenosis is another congenital disorder.
This is where you get hypertrophy of the pyloric smooth muscle.
It's more common in males.
Here's the idea.
Of course, you've got the esophagus,
and then you've got the stomach coming off the esophagus,
and eventually you recognize that the stomach feeds into the duodenum,
and in order for food to go from the stomach into the duodenum,
it's got to cross this sphincter called the pyloric sphincter.
Now, what happens in pyloric stenosis is that you get thickening of the wall of the sphincter
because of hypertrophy of smooth muscle, which then creates a stenosis,
and a stenosis is basically just a tightening of that window,
so that now, because you've got tight stenosis here,
you can't get the food properly out of the stomach.
Now, what's important to note and what's interesting is that these babies,
when they're born, they're actually normal.
So there is no pyloric stenosis at birth, and that's actually high yield.
The pyloric stenosis develops about two weeks after birth,
and that's when it classically presents.
So why don't I put it this way?
It takes time for the stenosis to develop,
and then the patients will present two weeks after birth.
Now, how will they present?
Well, as they bring food in here,
it's not going to be able to pass through this area,
and that's going to build up pressure in the stomach.
And so eventually, as the pressure continues to build,
it's then going to result in the shooting of food this way,
and so you get projectile vomiting.
Another interesting thing that you can see
is that when you look at the abdomen of these babies,
because there's so much peristalsis of the stomach against this tight block,
that peristalsis can actually be visible on the abdomen.
When you do physical exam,
you can actually feel this area of hypertrophy of muscle,
and it feels like an olive-like mass.
It's just a tiny little olive in this baby's abdomen.
And the way by which you would treat
is you would cut away this muscle, which is called myotomy.
And so these are the key clinical features,
and they're all based on the anatomy.
Again, it presents usually two weeks after birth.
So the clinical features are listed here in your text.
The only thing I would like to point out here,
in addition to what I've already said,
is that when you get that vomiting, the vomiting is non-bilious.
You know, the contents of the abdomen have not yet met the bile,
because that would occur in the duodenum after the pyloric stenosis.
And so, just as a picture, very simplistically,
you realize that pyloric stenosis is here,
but the bile is coming in down here in the duodenum.
So this food that goes up is not going to have bile within it.
So that's non-bilious vomiting.
Everything else I've already explained,
and so you can review this in your text as well.
Acute gastritis is very straightforward.
Maybe it'd be best, actually, to take a step back
and just do a global picture of gastritis before we move on.
So when you think about gastritis,
what you should remind yourselves of is that there's two types.
There is acute gastritis, and there is chronic gastritis.
And acute gastritis is basically a story of burning of the stomach by acid.
So when you have acid and it burns the stomach,
the surface of the stomach, that's called acute gastritis.
Now let's recall that it would basically be a function of one of two things.
In acute gastritis, either you're going to have increased acid production,
that's one way by which you might get acute gastritis,
or the other way would be that you would have decreased protection of the mucosa.
Remember that the key protective mechanism against burning of the stomach by acid
is that you've got a protective mucosa.
So you would have decreased protection from the mucosa.
All right, so these are the two ways, M-U-C-O-S-A, sorry about that.
These are the two ways in which you're going to get acute gastritis.
Either there'll be too much acid or there won't be enough protection.
And so, of course, if there's an imbalance here,
that will result in an acid damage to the mucosa of the stomach.
And that's the key thing in acute gastritis.
Chronic gastritis, on the other hand, can be subdivided into two types based on etiology.
And so the first type is called chronic autoimmune gastritis.
And the second type is called chronic H. pylori gastritis.
So these are the two types.
And we'll discuss these in much more detail as we move forward.
I'm just trying to lay down a global picture in your mind.
So again, acute gastritis, acid damage to the mucosa,
which would be due to an imbalance between the mucosal protection and the acidic environment.
And then chronic gastritis will be subdivided into two types.
There's an autoimmune type, which is the less common type.
And then there's an H. pylori induced type, which is obviously the most common type.
Now let's start with our discussion of acute gastritis.
So I told you that acute gastritis is acidic damage to the mucosa.
And there's an imbalance between the mucosal defenses and the acidic environment.
Let's very quickly talk about the mucosal defenses.
So there are several types of defenses that we have,
which are present within the mucosa that protect against acid.
So for example, let's say that this is the mucosa.
You know that the mucosa is lined by epithelium.
Let me remind you from histology that these epithelial cells are also known as foveolar cells.
Now the foveolar cells, they produce mucus, and that makes a mucus layer.
And that, of course, protects the cells.
There's also a ton of bicarb secretion, which then helps to neutralize any acid that might come anywhere near these cells.
It's important to have a normal blood supply,
because the normal blood supply provides nutrients to this mucosa to keep it alive and healthy.
And also the normal blood supply has the ability to pick up acid,
so that if some acid were actually to leak through this barrier,
the blood supply could actually take the acid away from that particular region.
And so your defenses, these are your key defenses that protect you against the acidic environment of the stomach.
Now, once you understand that, you can then go into a discussion of the risk factors of acute gastritis.
So for example, the first risk factor would be a severe burn.
That's also called a curling ulcer when the patients get ulceration in the context of a severe burn.
Now what's the idea here?
Well, when patients get severe burn, one of the complications is hypovolemia.
And if you have hypovolemia, there's going to be less blood flow to the stomach.
And if you have less blood flow to the stomach, then the mucosa is not going to receive as much nutrients,
and you're also not going to be able to sweep away the acid with the blood flow, the way I described earlier.
So blood flow is essential for that protective barrier,
and if you don't have good blood flow, it's going to increase the risk for developing acute gastritis.
Now, another risk factor would be NSAIDs, and the idea here is that prostaglandins that are normally produced by cyclooxygenase of the foveolar cells
are essential for creating this protective barrier.
For example, one thing that the prostaglandins do is that they decrease acid production,
so that protects the mucosa by decreasing the acid.
They also stimulate the ability of the cells to produce mucus and bicarb, so that would be protective.
They also increase the blood flow to the mucosal barrier, so that that can increase both the nutrients as well as the ability to sweep away acid.
And so, again, without your prostaglandins, you're going to be in big trouble.
And so what the NSAIDs do is they knock out the prostaglandins, and when you knock out the prostaglandins,
you're going to lose all of those beneficial effects of the prostaglandins.
That will increase the risk for acute gastritis.
Heavy alcohol consumption can do it as well.
Alcohol is basically a toxin.
It will directly damage the mucosa, allowing for the acid to then subsequently damage the stomach.
So that would be another cause.
Chemotherapy can also increase the risk for formation of acute gastritis.
And the idea here is that when you give chemotherapy, you're knocking out the cells that are turning over,
and if you knock out the cells that are turning over, then you're not going to be able to regenerate new cells in the mucosa of the stomach.
And so when you can't regenerate new cells, you're not going to have as good of a mucosal surface to protect against acid.
So chemotherapy knocks out your ability to regenerate the cells of the stomach, hence increasing the risk for acute gastritis.
Here's one very high-yield cause of acute gastritis, and that is increased intracranial pressure.
Examiner's love to go after this, and I'll explain why in a moment.
Increased intracranial pressure, when it results in acute gastritis, is also called a Cushing ulcer.
And here's the idea, is that when you get increased intracranial pressure, you're going to get increased vagal stimulation.
And that increased vagal stimulation is then going to result in increased acetylcholine.
And acetylcholine has the ability to bind the parietal cell receptor to increased acid production.
Let's just go back and remind ourselves of a couple of very simple but important points.
Remember that the cell in the stomach that makes the acid is called the parietal cell.
That's one important point.
And the parietal cell has three important receptors that can help to regulate the amount of acid that's produced.
There's an acetylcholine receptor, so acetylcholine can help to produce acid.
There's a gastrin receptor, so that gastrin can induce production of acid.
And then the third receptor is that there's a histamine receptor.
All three of these are high-yield physiology.
So any one of these substances, acetylcholine, gastrin, or histamine,
can actually induce the production of acid by the parietal cells.
So again, now with that in mind, when you go back and read what we say here,
increased intracranial pressure, of course, would increase vagal stimulation,
which would then increase acetylcholine,
which would then increase production of acid by the parietal cells.
If you have increased acid, that's going to increase the risk of having acid damage to the mucosa.
And the last example would be shock.
And the idea here is that when patients get shocked,
they get a severe decrease in their blood flow to vital organs.
And one of those areas where blood flow would decrease would be the stomach.
And, of course, a decreased blood flow will then result in an increased risk
for development of acute gastritis due to acidic damage.
Now let me remind you that patients who get shock actually get multiple ulcers,
and those are called stress ulcers.
And that's why most patients in the ICU are actually placed on, for example,
proton pump inhibitors to protect against the formation of multiple stress ulcers.
When patients get acidic damage, that's going to result in one of three possibilities.
You can simply just get superficial inflammation due to damage to the epithelium.
You can actually knock out the epithelium, and when you lose the epithelium,
that's called an erosion.
Or you can knock out the entire mucosal layer, and that would be called an ulceration.
So, again, when you knock out the epithelium, that's an erosion.
But when you knock out the mucosal layer, that is called an ulceration.
And so these are the consequences of the acidic damage.
Chronic gastritis, as I've already stated, can be divided into two types.
And it's based on the underlying etiology.
And I told you earlier that there's an autoimmune type, and then there's an H. pylori type.
In chronic autoimmune gastritis, you get autoimmune destruction of the parietal cells.
Now, recall that the parietal cells are predominantly present in the body and the fundus.
So let's go back and review.
Remember that when you think about the stomach, that's the esophagus there.
And then you know that the stomach is coming off, and when the stomach comes off,
you've got multiple regions.
So you've got here, this represents the cardia.
This represents the fundus, which would actually be a little bit higher like that.
And then there's a body here, and then there's an antrum here.
So those are the four regions of the stomach.
The cardia, the fundus, the body, and then the antrum.
Now, it's in the fundus in the body where you predominantly have your parietal cells.
And so in chronic autoimmune gastritis, what happens is that you get an autoimmune destruction
of the parietal cells in that particular region, in the body and the fundus.
And this is very high yield to know that in this particular case, it's in the body and the fundus.
Now, this is actually a T-cell mediated damage, so that it's a type 4 hypersensitivity reaction.
But as a consequence of that damage, what you get in the blood is antibodies against the parietal cells
or antibodies against intrinsic factor.
And I want to make it very clear.
These antibodies are not causing the damage.
They are a side effect of the damage.
They are a consequence of the damage, and they're useful for diagnosis.
Now, clinically, what's going to happen is as you begin to knock out the parietal cells,
you're going to begin to knock out the thickness of the mucosa.
And so the patients are going to get atrophy of the mucosa.
So that's going to be one clinical feature that we're going to see.
Another clinical feature is that because you're knocking out the parietal cells,
you're knocking out the ability to produce acid.
And so when you knock out the ability to produce acid,
what's going to happen is there's going to be something called achlorhydria.
And I've written that here in your notes here, where I say that achlorhydria will develop.
And what is achlorhydria?
Low acid production by the stomach.
Now, of course, if there's achlorhydria, you won't have good acid in the stomach,
and so the gastrin levels will increase because you've lost the negative feedback.
Gastrin is the key molecule that drives the parietal cells to produce acid.
So if there's low acid, there's going to be increased gastrin trying to make extra acid.
And that increased gastrin level will also be associated with G-cell hyperplasia in the antrum.
Let me remind you that it's the G-cells that make gastrin, and the G-cells are present in the antrum.
And so if there's going to be increased gastrin, it will be made by the G-cells,
and those G-cells will undergo hyperplasia in the antrum.
And all of this is high yield because it ties into a little bit of physiology.
Now, the third clinical feature will be that the patients will get megaloblastic anemia.
Now, why do they get megaloblastic anemia?
Well, remember that the parietal cells, which are being destroyed in this disorder, they make intrinsic factor.
An intrinsic factor is necessary for vitamin B12 absorption.
Remember that intrinsic factor binds vitamin B12 in the intestine, and then it goes to the terminal ileum,
and the terminal ileum recognizes the vitamin B12 intrinsic factor complex,
which then allows vitamin B12 to come into the body.
Well, if the patients have a destruction of their parietal cells, they won't be making intrinsic factor,
and if they're not making intrinsic factor, they can't bring in vitamin B12.
And of course, when they don't bring in vitamin B12, that'll result in megaloblastic anemia.
Now, that entire paradigm that I've just described is also called pernicious anemia,
again, due to a lack of intrinsic factor.
And actually, this is the most common cause of vitamin B12 deficiency.
So, chronic autoimmune gastritis, most common cause of vitamin B12 deficiency.
Now, these patients will also have an increased risk for gastric adenocarcinoma.
And the idea here is that the chronic inflammation is going to induce something called intestinal metaplasia.
And when you get intestinal metaplasia, that metaplasia is a pathologic metaplasia,
which will have an increased risk for the development of cancer.
Let me take a step back and remind you that normally, if you were to look at the wall of the stomach,
there would be no inflammatory cells.
All right?
So, you would not see any inflammatory cells in the wall of the stomach.
However, if you get chronic inflammation of the stomach,
now you've got a ton of inflammatory cells present in the wall of the stomach.
Well, the cells of the stomach will then undergo metaplasia,
because now they're seeing a ton of inflammatory cells,
and they'll start to form the cells that are normally in the presence of a ton of inflammatory cells.
And those are the intestinal cells.
Remember that in the intestine, you have pyre's patches with a bunch of inflammatory cells within it,
i.e. a bunch of lymphocytes.
And so, when you get a bunch of lymphocytes in the stomach,
you get this metaplasia where the stomach cells become like the intestinal cells.
And so, we call that, again, intestinal metaplasia.
Now, here's a classic picture of intestinal metaplasia.
And let me just remind you that from normal histology, these are your foveolar cells.
So, the foveolar cells don't have big circles of mucus within them.
And, of course, the foveolar cells are the normal cells that would be lining the surface of the stomach.
Now, here you can see that you've got these goblet cells with big circles of mucus within them.
And so, the presence of those large, big goblets of mucus, those are called goblet cells,
and they indicate intestinal metaplasia.
And this is a very high-yield principle to be aware of.
It goes back to a little bit of normal histology, and it goes back to a very important risk,
and that is the risk for gastric adenocarcinoma.
The second type of chronic gastritis is chronic H. pylori gastritis.
And this represents the vast majority of chronic gastritis, about 90% of cases.
Of course, it's due to H. pylori.
The H. pylori bug induces acute and chronic inflammation, which then results in gastritis.
The reason why H. pylori can induce acute and chronic inflammation is because it produces ureases and proteases,
which then result in inflammation and weakening of the mucosal defenses.
Now, it's important to note that H. pylori does not invade into the stomach.
It simply sits on the surface of the epithelium, but it produces these different byproducts,
which can then result in inflammation and weakening of the mucosal defenses.
The most common site is the antrum, and that's important because, again,
when you think about chronic gastritis, remember there's autoimmune, which involves the fundus in the body,
and then there's H. pylori, which involves the antrum.
So they involve very different regions of the stomach.
Here's a picture of H. pylori.
You can clearly see these little slender organisms.
So this is the classic picture of H. pylori.
Remember that they sit on top of the epithelium.
They do not invade into the stomach mucosa.
The presentation of patients with H. pylori is that they get epigastric abdominal pain,
and there's an increased risk for ulceration, and that's because with all this chronic inflammation,
you can develop an ulcer.
There's an increased risk for gastric adenocarcinoma, and that's because, again,
with this chronic inflammation, you're going to get an intestinal metoplasia,
and the intestinal metoplasia can eventually become cancer.
So there'll be an increased risk for adenocarcinoma.
And the third risk will be an increased risk for malt lymphoma.
Now, when you have all this chronic inflammation, what you're going to do is you're going to generate
germinal centers within the gastric wall.
And when you generate germinal centers within the gastric wall,
you're also going to generate post-germinal center B cells.
And when you generate post-germinal center B cells, remember that that actually represents
a special zone within your inflammatory infiltrate called the marginal zone.
Remember our discussion of how you can have a follicle, which represents the germinal center,
and then outside of the follicle, you can have something called the mantle,
and then outside of the mantle, you can have a marginal zone.
This goes back to our discussion of white blood cell pathology.
Now, the marginal zone only forms when there is some sort of chronic inflammatory state
or some sort of chronic inflammation, which necessitates the need for a post-germinal center B cell.
So, in this particular case, you've got this chronic inflammation, which then results in production
of these post-germinal center B cells, which then again results in the production of a marginal zone.
And it's this marginal zone that can eventually result in malt lymphoma.
Malt means a mucosa-associated lymphoid tissue, and then, of course, it's a lymphoma.
So, this is a B cell lymphoma that can classically be seen within the wall of the stomach.
Now, I've already discussed this in extreme detail when we did the white blood cell pathology lecture.
So, you can review it in your text there as well.
Now, what's interesting is you've kind of got three complications.
You had ulceration, cancer, and lymphoma.
And it's interesting that triple therapy is what's given,
and the triple therapy actually helps to reduce the risk for the three complications.
Now, that's just coincidental, obviously.
But the point is it helps to remind you of their three complications and the fact that you give triple therapy.
Of course, when you give triple therapy, you're going to resolve the gastritis.
And if you resolve the gastritis, the ulcer will resolve, if the patient has ulceration.
If the patient had intestinal metaplasia, that will resolve,
because remember from Chapter 1 of our text that metaplasia is reversible.
And then, if there was an increased inflammatory infiltrate with a risk of lymphoma,
of course, that inflammatory infiltrate will disappear once the gastritis disappears,
and so the risk of lymphoma will also disappear.
So triple therapy is essential to avoid the complications of H. pylori.
And, of course, it's also essential to simply just resolve the gastritis
in the clinical presentation that's associated with it.
Now, when you give triple therapy, you want to make sure that you've gotten rid of the bug.
And so the way by which you do that is you can look for urea in the breath,
because remember that the bug is making ureases,
and so it produces urea as a byproduct.
And so when there's lack of urea in the breath, that will tell you that the bug has been killed.
Another way to check is to look at the stool.
And in the stool, you'll see lack of H. pylori antigen.
So that would also be helpful to confirm eradication.
The next discussion is peptic ulcer disease.
And in peptic ulcer disease, the idea here is that you get a solitary ulcer of the mucosa
that either involves the proximal duodenum, 90% of the time it's in the proximal duodenum,
or in the distal stomach.
Now, when you get a duodenal ulcer, it's almost always due to H. pylori.
That is the number one way by which duodenal ulcers can form.
However, rarely, it can also be due to ZE syndrome.
Remember that ZE syndrome is when a patient has a gastronoma.
The gastronoma is a tumor that produces excess gastrin.
The gastrin goes into the blood.
It hits the parietal cells, and the parietal cells then begin to secrete massive amounts of acid.
And the production of massive amounts of acid can result in a peptic ulcer disease with a duodenal ulcer.
And in ZE syndrome, you can also have multiple ulcers.
You can also have ulcers that extend into the jejunum, etc.
But anyway, that's one way by which a duodenal ulcer can arise.
Now, how is this going to present?
Whether it be due to H. pylori or ZE syndrome, for example, it will present with epigastric pain that improves with meals.
Now, when a patient takes a meal, the duodenum begins to prepare itself for the potential receiving of that acid bolus from the stomach.
And so immediately, the duodenum begins to increase its defenses and produce neutralizing substances that will protect it against the acid that's eventually coming from the stomach.
Those protective mechanisms are also going to improve the pain, and that's why the pain improves with meals.
Now, the way by which you could prove that there's a duodenal ulcer and confirm the etiology is to do endoscopic biopsy.
And that would show the ulcer along with hypertrophy of the Bruner's glands.
And the Bruner's glands are glands present within the duodenum, the wall of the duodenum, that, of course, produce a mucus-like substance.
And so, of course, there would be excess mucus-like substance to try to protect against this damage that's occurring with a duodenal ulcer.
Now, one of the complications of a duodenal ulcer is that it can rupture.
And this would, one of the complications of rupture is that you can get bleeding from the gastroduodenal artery, or you can get acute pancreatitis.
Why don't I take a step back and remind you that you can have ulceration on the anterior wall or the posterior wall.
The most common site would be the anterior wall.
However, were it to occur along the posterior wall, the complication would be that you could get rupture from the gastroduodenal artery.
That's because that runs at the posterior aspect of the duodenum.
Or you could actually activate the pancreas and the pancreatic enzymes and create an acute pancreatitis.
Now, of course, both of these would be a complication of posterior ulcers.
And I think in your text, it actually says that the gastroduodenal artery bleeding is due to anterior ulcers.
So I would advise you or ask that you correct that in the text at this point and make sure that you make it clear that both of these are a complication of posterior ulcers.
Now, the second type of peptic ulcer disease would be a gastric ulcer.
This is usually due to H. pylori, but not always.
And there are other causes, including NSAIDs and bile reflux.
So we could say perhaps like 70% of gastric ulcers due to H. pylori, maybe another 20% is due to NSAIDs.
So the two big causes, H. pylori and NSAIDs, but bile reflux is also an important cause.
This is going to present with epigastric pain, and it worsens with meals.
The moment you take a meal, acid begins to generate within the stomach to digest that food,
and so the pain is going to worsen with a meal.
Now, the ulcer is usually located on the lesser curvature of the antrum,
and rupture would carry a risk of bleeding from the left gastric artery.
Remember that the left gastric artery, it runs along the lesser curvature of the antrum,
and so if there's rupture, you can get bleeding from the left gastric artery.
Now, one of the differential diagnoses when you have an ulcer in the GI tract is cancer,
so we always got to think about cancer.
And so when we have peptic ulcer disease, one of the things that comes to mind is,
is this really peptic ulcer disease due to, for example, H. pylori, or is it cancer?
Well, let me start the discussion by saying that duodenal ulcers are almost never malignant,
and so that's a very important principle.
In fact, duodenal carcinoma is super, super rare.
In fact, when you think about the cancers that you study in the GI tract,
you study esophageal cancer, you study stomach cancer, you study colon cancer,
you haven't really studied a lot about small bowel cancer,
and that's because duodenal cancer is very, very rare.
So duodenal ulcers are almost never malignant, and they're usually not biopsied.
So we don't necessarily have to worry about that when we think about the differential diagnosis of cancer.
And, of course, most peptic ulcer disease is duodenal.
However, when you have a gastric ulcer, you really do have to worry about cancer,
and that's because gastric cancer can also create ulceration.
And so it's very important to be familiar with the morphology of the ulcer,
whether it be benign or malignant.
So what are features that would suggest that it's benign,
and what are features that would suggest that it's malignant?
So this is what a benign ulcer looks like.
And the most important thing about this benign ulcer is that, number one, it's small.
That's a key feature is that the ulcer is small.
Number two, it's punched out.
It looks like somebody took a hole puncher and punched out this hole.
And number three, the margins next to it, when you look at the adjacent tissue next to it,
it's not piling up.
It's just sort of normal.
It's just flat and normal.
And so that's the important feature of a benign ulcer.
Of course, why is this important?
Because if you're the endoscopist and you're going in and taking a look at the stomach via scope,
you're going to look at the ulcer and you're going to try to make a guess
as to whether you think it's benign or malignant.
And so benign features such as a small ulcer that looks punched out
with no heaping up of the mucosa on the edge of the ulcer,
no piling up of the mucosa on the edge of the ulcer,
these are all features that suggest that you're dealing with a benign ulcer.
Now, on the other hand, a malignant ulcer, it looks irregular.
It doesn't look punched out.
And on top of that, it's much larger.
It's much bigger than that ulcer that I just showed you.
And on top of that, you can see all this piling up of the mucosa at the edge of the ulcer.
And that also is a feature that's worrisome for malignancy.
Of course, the only way to make the final determination would be to do biopsy.
Now, this brings us to a discussion of gastric cancer.
And so let's remind ourselves that gastric carcinoma is a malignant proliferation
of surface epithelial cells.
Those epithelial cells are columnar cells.
So we're going to get an adenocarcinoma.
All right?
So gastric carcinoma is basically an adenocarcinoma.
Now, you can divide gastric carcinoma into two types.
There's an intestinal type and a diffuse type.
In the intestinal type, you get a large irregular ulcer with heaped up margins,
as I've just described.
And this most commonly involves the lesser curvature of the antrum.
Now, remember that the lesser curvature of the antrum is exactly the same place
where we got stomach ulcers and peptic ulcer disease.
And so, again, that's why it's so important to know the differences between benign ulcers
and malignant ulcers and how they would be distinguished morphologically.
The risk factors for the intestinal type include intestinal menoplasia.
Of course, that's very straightforward,
because intestinal menoplasia would give you the intestinal type.
Now, let's go back and remind ourselves,
what are things that would give you intestinal menoplasia?
Well, number one, chronic autoimmune gastritis gives you intestinal menoplasia.
And number two, chronic H. pylori gastritis gives you intestinal menoplasia.
So those are the two key risk factors.
Also, an important risk factor is nitrosamines, especially in smoked foods.
So remember from our discussion in the neoplasia chapter that I mentioned about how nitrosamines
are a carcinogen.
They're present in smoked foods.
And they help to explain the increased incidence of stomach cancer in Japan.
And then a final important thing to remember is that patients who have blood type A,
they have an increased risk of developing the intestinal type of stomach cancer.
It's a very strange thing, but you've got to remember it.
And so the way I do that is just remember that when we abbreviate carcinoma, we always just say CA,
like adenos CA or squamous CA.
At least that's the way that we do it as pathologists.
And so that A, maybe that'll help you remember that there's an association of intestinal type
of stomach cancer with blood type A.
Now, the second type of stomach cancer, which is much less common but is super important
and super high yield on board exams, is called the diffuse type.
In the diffuse type, what happens is that you get signet ring cells that diffusely infiltrate
the gastric wall.
And when they diffusely infiltrate the gastric wall, that results in cancer plus a reaction
to that cancer.
That reaction is called desmoplasia, which results in a thickening of the stomach wall
creating something called linitis plastica.
Now, there's a little bit of explanation here before we can move forward.
First of all, what's a signet ring cell?
A signet ring cell is a cell that has its nucleus pushed off to the very edge.
And what's pushing off the nucleus to the very edge is the production of mucus by the tumor
cells or mucin by the tumor cells, which often sits in a little circular space.
So that's the first point.
That's a signet ring cell.
Now, in the diffuse type, these signet ring cells, they diffusely infiltrate the wall of
the stomach.
And that results in something called desmoplasia.
What's desmoplasia?
Desmoplasia is a reactive response of the stroma.
So it's just basically fibrous tissue in some blood vessels that occurs in response to the
invasive tumor.
And so this desmoplasia then results in thickening of the stomach wall so that these patients get
linitis plastica.
Now, important to note, this is not associated with H. pylori.
It's not associated with intestinal metoplasia.
And it's not associated with nitrosamines.
Here's a picture of the diffuse type in which you have thickening of the stomach wall with
this white fibrous kind of reaction called desmoplasia.
Were you to do a biopsy, you would see these signet ring cells.
Here's a classic cell.
Here's a classic signet ring cell.
You can see that there's a circular mucus, and it's pushed off the nucleus to one edge
of the cell.
And so this is a very important feature to be aware of, and that is that in the diffuse
type, you get signet ring cells.
So let me just summarize very briefly.
There's two types of stomach cancer.
There's an intestinal type, which produces an ulcer.
And then there is a diffuse type, which diffusely thickens the wall of the stomach, on gross
exam, and is characterized by signet ring cells.
Now, gastric carcinoma, whether it be the diffuse type or whether it be the intestinal type,
it presents late.
The classic signs are going to be weight loss, abdominal pain, anemia, and they get early
satiety.
And early satiety would be classic in the diffuse type because in that particular case, you've
got this thickening and fibrosis of the wall.
And so the stomach can't expand, and the patients would feel full with a little bit of food.
That's called early satiety.
Now, there are some interesting signs that can be associated with gastric carcinoma.
For example, one thing that can be seen with gastric carcinoma is something called acanthrosis
nigricans, where you get a thickening and darkening of the skin, in particular in the axillary region.
So that can be a sign that the patient has gastric carcinoma.
Another very interesting sign is called the lesser trelot sign.
And this is where the patients get dozens of seborrheic keratosis all over their skin
that just sort of arise all of a sudden.
And this can also be seen with gastric carcinoma.
And you really want to know that association.
It's high yield.
Now, gastric carcinoma will spread to the lymph nodes.
It's a cancer.
And one of the interesting lymph nodes that it can often spread to is the left supraclavicular
node.
And that's called Verkau's node.
And that's one of the nodes that drains the stomach.
So the left supraclavicular node is important to be aware of in the context of gastric carcinoma.
When you get distant metastases, usually it involves the liver.
However, there are some classic sites to be aware of.
One is the peri-umbilical region.
And so we can get metastases of stomach cancer to the peri-umbilical region.
That's called the Sister Mary Joseph nodule.
And that's classically seen with the intestinal type of gastric cancer.
Another interesting place that you can have metastasis to is the bilateral ovaries.
And when you get bilateral ovary involvement by gastric cancer, that's called a Kruckenberg
tumor.
And again, that's classically seen with the diffuse type.
Again, the diffuse type has signet ring cells.
Those signet ring cells make mucus.
And remember that a Kruckenberg tumor is basically defined as bilateral mucinous carcinoma
involving the ovary as a metastatic phenomenon.
And so that's an important association, diffuse type resulting in Kruckenberg tumor.
And that's the end of our stomach section.
The next section is small bowel.